<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The beauty of unity in a sermon preached at Preston in Lancashire at the opening of the Guide-merchant held there, September 4, 1682 / by Richard Wroe ...</title>
            <author>Wroe, Richard, 1641-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3726</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31851</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12269677</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12269677</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58190</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67182)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58190)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1516:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The beauty of unity in a sermon preached at Preston in Lancashire at the opening of the Guide-merchant held there, September 4, 1682 / by Richard Wroe ...</title>
                  <author>Wroe, Richard, 1641-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benj. Tooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXII [1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:58190:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58190:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Beauty of Vnity.</hi> IN A SERMON PREACHED AT <hi>PRESTON</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> At the Opening of the GUILD-MERCHANT held There. <hi>September</hi> 4. 1682.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD WROE, <hi>B. D.</hi> and Chaplain to the Lord Biſhop of <hi>CHESTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Tooke,</hi> at the Ship in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard.</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:58190:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58190:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful <hi>ROGER S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DELL,</hi> Mayor of <hi>PRESTON,</hi> And to the ALDERMEN and COMMON-COUNCIL of that Ancient BOROUGH.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen I received the intimation of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that I would preach your <hi>Guild-Sermon,</hi> I was very ready to comply with your requeſt, that I might manifeſt my willingneſs to ſerve <hi>you,</hi> and own that reſpect which you were pleaſed to ſhew me by making it the <hi>unanimous Vote</hi> of your <hi>Common-Council.</hi> But when I was importun'd by <hi>you,</hi> and thoſe <hi>worthy Perſons</hi> that were preſent to honour your Solemnity, to <hi>Publiſh</hi> what I had <hi>Preach'd</hi> to you, I was much more unwilling to yield to it, being averſe to appear in <hi>Print,</hi> and loth to be expoſed to the Cenſures of a Critical Age. But I have denied my ſelf that I may not ſeem to deny you any thing: and in this
<pb facs="tcp:58190:3"/> only am ambitious that I may be able to gratifie ſo <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> a <hi>Corporation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſolemnity</hi> of a <hi>Guild-Merchant</hi> is peculiar to your Town, and (I think) no where elſe obſerved in <hi>England,</hi> at leaſt not with that <hi>Formality</hi> and <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur,</hi> and with that <hi>reſpect</hi> and <hi>free Entertainment</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to thoſe <hi>Perſons</hi> of <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> that from all parts flock to ſee it, and are wellcomed with the hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary <hi>Freedom</hi> of your <hi>Corporation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems ſtrange that ſo ancient and laudable a Cuſtom ſhould be ſingular: and if an account of your decent and regular management of it were made publick, I doubt not but it would invite other places to follow your example.</p>
            <p>But as this is your peculiar <hi>Priviledg,</hi> ſo I reckon it your great <hi>happineſs</hi> that you live like a Fraternity, and are not more careful of your own <hi>Franchiſes,</hi> than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Laws, ſuch eſpecially as are made to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Society by preventing Diſſenſion and Diviſion: and you may juſtly glory in this, that for ſundry years laſt paſt, no <hi>Separate Meeting,</hi> or <hi>Seditious Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> has diſturbed the Peace of your <hi>Corporation,</hi> or divided you into <hi>Parties</hi> and <hi>Factions,</hi> but you have lived as <hi>Brethren</hi> in Peace and Unity, and worſhipped <hi>God</hi> with Order and Uniformity.</p>
            <p>I heartily wiſh it may always be the honor of your <hi>Corporation,</hi> to be famous for <hi>Agreement</hi> and <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> and have endeavoured all I could to endear it in the
<pb facs="tcp:58190:3"/> enſuing Diſcourſe: which if it may any way contribute to ſo good an effect, I have my <hi>deſign,</hi> and let <hi>God</hi> have the <hi>Glory.</hi> I am ſure the meaning was <hi>honeſt,</hi> to perſuade to <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and promote <hi>Union</hi> and <hi>Agreement,</hi> and will hope it may be <hi>ſerviceable</hi> to that end, ſince <hi>you</hi> were pleaſed to think it ſo. I know not what entertainment it may find amongſt thoſe that <hi>read</hi> it: but I cannot wiſh for a more kind reception than it had from them that heard it: what ever others judg of it, it challenges a favourable Conſtruction from <hi>you</hi> whoſe Importunity made it Publick; and thereby have given me an Opportunity to tell the World, how much I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble and Obedient Servant, RICHARD WROE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:58190:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58190:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON Pſalm CXXXIII. 1.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Behold, how good and how pleaſant it is, for Brethren to dwell together in Unity.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">U</seg>Nity is a word that carries joy and pleaſantneſs in its ſound; a thing ſo Divine and Excellent, that among all the perfections of this inferior World, there is no more lively Reſemblance, or fairer Emblem of Heavens Glory; which is therefore perfect, becauſe it cannot be confounded by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, nor diſturb'd by diſagreement, but is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated in an eternal Unity. And were there Art equal to the Subject, to ſet out its graceful Linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and comely Proportions, it would be found moſt true of this Divine Grace of <hi>Unity,</hi> what has
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58190:5"/> been ſaid of <hi>Virtue</hi> by ſome of the Ancients, that ſhe is ſo lovely in her ſelf, and ſo comely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, that could ſhe be ſeen embodyed, all the Beholders would be raviſhed with her Beauty, and fall in love with her. But though I cannot hope to reach its due Character, or make a juſt tranſcript of ſo fair an Original, yet I ſhall expoſe her to your view in the Pſalmiſts Deſcription of her Beauty, <hi>Behold, how good and how pleaſant it is, for Brethren to dwell together in Unity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſubject never unſeaſonable; and now very ſuitable to the times we live in, and proper to the Occaſion we are met about. For when our diviſions are ſo many, and our diſtractions ſo great; when the Peace of the Church is rent by Schiſm, and that of the State endanger'd by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Diſcontent, what remedy can be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to heal our Diſtempers, and cloſe up our Wounds, but Agreement and Unity? and where ſhall we hope to behold that pleaſant proſpect ſooner than among them who are already embo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed into an united Society, by mutual Intereſts, and particular Obligations? And when can we more properly Diſcourſe of it, than before a <hi>Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity,</hi> whoſe very Eſſence conſiſts in Unity? their Priviledges being the reſult of mutual Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and the very Title of <hi>Corporation,</hi> implying that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58190:5"/> Correſpondence and Relation which the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Body have both to the whole, and to one another.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore beſpeak your attention, both as Brethren, adopted into one <hi>Common Fraternity</hi> (which you are here met to repreſent;) and as fellow Members of the ſame Body, Subjects of the ſame Government, whoſe Peace and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity I hope you all wiſh well to and pray for; whilſt I endeavour to recommend to you the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies and advantages of Unity, which is the only ſolid and laſting Foundation of our peace and ſettlement both in Church and State.</p>
            <p>For the Deſign of general Unity muſt firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at particular perſons and places: and there is no hopes to ſee its happy Influence Publick and Univerſal, till the exerciſe of it be made exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary in the leſſer Societies of <hi>Families,</hi> and the larger <hi>Corporations</hi> of Towns and Cities.</p>
            <p>May <hi>you</hi> lead the way; and ſet the pattern of a compleat <hi>Fraternity,</hi> united not only in <hi>Franchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Priviledges,</hi> but in mind and affections; and ſo begin that bleſſed Concord which would undoubtedly make us an happy people among our ſelves, and a terror to the Nations round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. Were our Towns and Cities model'd as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> once was, a City at Unity with it ſelf;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58190:6"/> we might then expect to ſee that <hi>thorough Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> which has been ſo long talk'd of, but is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible ever to be effected by Schiſm and Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Would they that pretend to contend ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly for the Faith, but as zealouſly endeavour to keep the Unity of the Faith in the bond of Peace; would every one of us in his own Sphere contribute his Prayers and Endeavours hereto, we ſhould then rejoyce to behold the bleſſed and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py effects of Agreement and Unity, and by joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful experience find, <hi>how good and pleaſant it is, for Brethren to dwell together in Unity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Words being an Argument for Unity, it may ſeem leſs proper to divide them; and my deſign being to ſet out the excellency and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of this Divine Grace, I ſhall purſue it in the Characters here given in the Pſalmiſts Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, 'tis both <hi>good and pleaſant.</hi> Which two, are prevailing Arguments, and the moſt forcible perſwaſives to engage our love and affections to any thing recommended to us, for theſe two ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſway mens choice; and all their purſuits are after what they apprehend as <hi>good or pleaſant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I preſs the Motives to Unity, it ſeems neceſſary to know what it is: ſince it is ſo rare to be met with, that it ſeems to be little un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; though indeed it is generally better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood than practiſed.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58190:6"/>
            <p>Unity, however ſingle in it ſelf, yet is diverſifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by its Object; and ſo is as various, as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects in which men may be united: but I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance only in three ſorts, both as moſt compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive, and chiefly to be endeavoured after. 1. <hi>An Unity in Faith and Profeſſion. 2. In Worſhip and Practice. 3. In Mind and Affection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Unity in Faith and Profeſſion:</hi> which is ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Apoſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 13. Which is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to the being of a Chriſtian; who by Faith is incorporated into the body of Chriſt; and by Unity of the Faith, is conjoyned to the members of that Body, which are all united un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one head. For <hi>the Faith was once delivered,</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Jude</hi>) and being but once delivered, can be but <hi>One:</hi> and as there is no way to be ſaved but by Faith, ſo there is but one Faith to be ſaved by: and therefore they that hope to receive the end of their Faith, the ſalvation of their Souls, muſt maintain the Unity of the Faith, which is loſt if divided; and is no Faith, if not the ſame that was <hi>once delivered.</hi> In this reſpect, we make it part of our Chriſtian Profeſſion to believe <hi>One Catholick Church:</hi> becauſe all agreeing in the ſame Faith, though the Members be many, yet the Church is but one, becauſe the Faith is but one: for there is but one Lord, and one Faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 5.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58190:7"/> One Lord, as the Foundation of all: and one Faith, whereby we aſſent to thoſe truths which were received from Chriſt by the Apoſtles, and by them delivered to Believers, who are therefore all Members of one and the ſame Church, becauſe they profeſs one and the ſame Faith. Now as we cannot be Chriſtians without Faith, ſo we cannot be of that <hi>One Catholick Church,</hi> without the Unity of it; and therefore (as St. <hi>Jude</hi> exhorts) ought <hi>to contend earneſtly for that Faith once delivered:</hi> that (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> preſſes it) <hi>we may keep the Unity of it in the bond of Peace.</hi> For we may contend earneſtly in this Caſe without breach of Peace or Charity: ſince the end of this holy contention, is an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Unity, namely of <hi>Faith and Profeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. There is an Unity in <hi>Worſhip and Practice.</hi> Which is conſequent on the former; when they that agree in the ſame Profeſſion, wear the ſame Badg and Livery, and are known by the ſame ſigns and ſymbols of Worſhip and Communion. This is that Unity of the Spirit, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 3. or Spiritual Unity, both as an effect of the Spirit, and a ſign of Spirituality; when we manifeſt our Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Faith by the correſpondence of our Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, whether in the ſame Rites of Worſhip, or the expreſſions of our Chriſtian Communion: thus we are made one by Worſhipping the ſame God,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58190:7"/> in one and the ſame manner. We become one by <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> the Sacrament of our Initiation, which being (as the Apoſtle ſays) <hi>but one,</hi> they which are admitted to it, in receiving it are <hi>one,</hi> and we are made <hi>one</hi> by participating of the ſame Supper of the Lord, who commanded, <hi>Eat ye all of this,</hi> and <hi>drink ye all of this;</hi> and ſo by communicating of <hi>one,</hi> become as to that Communication <hi>one;</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 7. We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many, are <hi>one</hi> Bread, and <hi>one</hi> Body, for we are all partakers of that <hi>one</hi> Bread. So that, when we liſt our ſelves under the ſame Banner, as we do in our <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and engage in the ſame Warfare, againſt the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh, whoſe Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip we renounce, and declare enmity againſt them: when we all participate of the <hi>ſame Body,</hi> whereof we are all Members, and like the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> all eat the ſame ſpiritual meat, and all drink the ſame ſpiritual drink: when with the firſt <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Church, we continue in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip, and in breaking of Bread, and in Prayer,</hi> when we are unanimous in the Worſhip of God, and the holy Offices of Religion, then do we hold faſt the Bond of Unity, and maintain the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the faithful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Unity of Mind and Affection.</hi> Which is the <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Spirit in the bond of Peace;</hi> that great badg
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58190:8"/> of Chriſtianity: the new Commandment that the Son of God preſcrib'd to his followers: that dying Legacy which he bequeathed to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that they ſhould love one another: that Unity which the Apoſtles ſo frequently and pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically preſs in their Epiſtles. St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> 2 Epiſt. 13. 11, <hi>Be of one mind, and live in Peace:</hi> to the <hi>Philippians 2. 2, That ye be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one mind.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> to the <hi>diſperſed Chriſtians,</hi> 1 Ep. 3. 8. <hi>Finally be ye all of one mind, having compaſſion one of another, love as Brethren, be pittiful, be cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous:</hi> This is the peculiar Badg of our Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which in its Nature and Deſign is a Religion of Love and Unity; and nothing unites more ſtrictly than kindneſs and affection. For as in the Body Natural, the Members however different in ſhape, and diſtant in ſite from one another, yet being all animated by the ſame Soul, become one Body; ſo the collective Body of Chriſtians how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever diſtant in Place, or differing in Language, yet being all of one mind and affection, make up one Body, the Church of Chriſt. On which account we offer up our Prayers to God for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and protection of the <hi>Church Catholick,</hi> to teſtifie our Unity with all the Members of that Body, and expreſs our hearty wiſhes for their welfare and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58190:8"/> proſperity: and though the Goſpel has extended our Charity, and made it univerſal, yet we are to have a more peculiar regard and love to them that are of the houſhold of Faith. Chriſtians are all Brethren, and thereby obliged to all the endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Brotherly Kindneſs and Affection; and when their <hi>Unity in the Faith, and Agreement in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> is compleated by the <hi>Concord of their Mind and Affections,</hi> there needs nothing more to make that perfect harmony which was once beheld in the Primitive Church, when <hi>the whole multitude of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers were all of one heart, and of one ſoul,</hi> Acts 4. 32. a joyful proſpect to behold, and lovely to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: that which raiſed envy in their Enemies, yet aſtoniſhment withal, <hi>Ecce quàm ſe mutuò diligunt Chriſtiani, behold</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>how Chriſtians love one another!</hi> but a raviſhing ſight to them that wiſh well to <hi>Sion,</hi> to ſee Brethren ſo dwell together in Unity.</p>
            <p>I know there are other kinds of Unity beſides theſe already mentioned; as Unity of <hi>Diſcipline and Government.</hi> Wherein, that the Chriſtian Churches did once all agree, ſeems plain from hence, that all ſides admit this as a great Truth; that is the beſt Form of Government which comes neareſt to the Primitive Platform: ſo that in the Primitive Church there was an Unity of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58190:9"/> the ſame Order of Men, the ſame Form of Government in all the Churches of Chriſt. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py had it been, had it received no alteration: hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py were we, were all our differences in that reſpect ſilenced into an amicable agreement: that as there is no <hi>Church,</hi> where there is no <hi>Order,</hi> no <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry;</hi> ſo we might all be of one and the ſame <hi>Church,</hi> by enjoying the ſame <hi>Order and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is alſo an Unity <hi>of Opinion;</hi> when men not only build upon the ſame Foundation, but raiſe the ſame ſuperſtructure, and agree not only in fundamentals, but ſhake hands alſo in leſs neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary truths, and have the ſame Sentiments and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, as well as Intereſts, in all things. An Unity that may be ſeen in Parties and Factions, eſpecially to promote an Intereſt, or ſecure a Deſign, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe is very rare to be met with. For as long as there are men of different Complexions, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Intereſts, there will be different Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and diſagreeing Opinions among them. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, that mens Tempers and Complexions ſtrongly incline them to ſome Opinions more than others: and no leſs evident it is, that the prejudices of Education, Acquaintance, and Cuſtom, do no leſs ſtrongly byaſs mens fancies with kindneſs to ſome Opinions, and a diſlike of others: ſo that till
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58190:9"/> all men are caſt in the ſame mold, and act upon the ſame Principles, and drive on the ſame end and deſign, Unity in Opinion is not like to be Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal.</p>
            <p>Indeed both this and the other, are rather to be wiſh'd than hoped for, for till men be willing to part with their <hi>Opinions</hi> (which yet few men are) there is ſmall hopes of Union that way; and till men become Humble and Obedient to the <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Government of the Church,</hi> no hopes to be united under any one Form. Beſides, that Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons encreaſe with the age of the World, and are daily multiplyed; and men grow more fond of their own Form of Diſcipline, and more averſe to all others. So that there is ſmall hopes of a perfect correſpondence in all things, till we come to that happy Union which the Apoſtle deſcribes, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 13. till we all come in the Unity of the Faith, and of the knowledg of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But if we cannot hope to ſee them, yet we may and ought to purſue after them; which would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of us in his ſeveral capacity ſincerely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, we ſhould enjoy that bleſſing of the Lord, to behold <hi>Truth and Unity met together, to ſee Righteouſneſs and Peace kiſs each other:</hi> and the only
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58190:10"/> method to purſue thoſe ends a right, is to maintain inviolable that threefold Unity, <hi>in Faith, in Worſhip, and Affection,</hi> which is indiſpenſably neceſſary to make us One with that Body whereof Chriſt is the head. For Unity in the Faith is <hi>Catholick Unity,</hi> without which we cannot be Members of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt. Unity in Worſhip, <hi>is Church Unity,</hi> without which we cannot hold the <hi>Communion of Saints;</hi> and Unity in Mind and Affection, is that Unity <hi>of Charity,</hi> without which we violate the Commands and Obligations of the Goſpel. But if we keep theſe intire, and twiſt this threefold cord, we make it ſtrong, and not eaſie to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. And when our Faith is One; and our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip uniform and agreeable, and our minds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire in united affections, we then wear his Livery whoſe Coat was ſeamleſs, the Emblem of Unity, not rent by Schiſm, nor torn by Separation; then <hi>like Brethren we dwell together in Unity:</hi> and how good and pleaſant that is to behold, is next to be made out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>'Tis good and pleaſant:</hi> excellent properties to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recommend a thing to our love and affections: for good is the great Object of our choice: And What more endearing than that which is good and pleaſant too? 'tis <hi>good,</hi> that intimates its ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and uſefulneſs: 'tis <hi>pleaſant,</hi> that implies its
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58190:10"/> delight and comelineſs. We'l ſurvey each proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty diſtinctly, that we may better behold its perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Its Neceſſity and Uſefulneſs.</hi> Of which we need no other Evidence, than the ſtrong Enforcements and Obligations which the Goſpel lays upon us to Unity, and the powerful Arguments wherewith the Apoſtles of Chriſt preſs it upon his Diſciples and Followers. I inſtance only in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and obſerve in this Argument, 1. The ſtrength of his Reaſoning. 2. The perſuaſiveneſs of his Oratory: The one is, that every thing in our Religion is an Argument to Unity, as you have it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 4, 5. there is <hi>one</hi> Body, and <hi>one</hi> Spirit, and <hi>one</hi> Hope of our Calling; <hi>one</hi> Lord, <hi>one</hi> Faith, <hi>one</hi> Baptiſm, <hi>one</hi> God and Father of all: every thing in our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is <hi>one;</hi> and ſo ought all they to be who are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes to that Religion. The other is, his power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eloquence, and perſuaſive Rhetorick, whilſt perſuading his <hi>Philippians</hi> to love and amity; and perhaps in no <hi>Author</hi> whatſoever, occurs a more pathetick and endearing ſtrain, than that in which he wooes and beſeeches them to <hi>Unity and Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> Phil. 2. 1, 2, <hi>If there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercies, fulfil ye my joy, that ye be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58190:11"/> mind; per ſanctum amicitiae nomen; per chara amoris pignora; per mutuò datam fidem:</hi> theſe are powerful Charms, but far leſs prevailing Oratory <hi>than</hi> the Apoſtle here uſed to preſs the <hi>Philippians</hi> to be of <hi>one accord, of one mind;</hi> and no doubt but the great earneſtneſs wherewith the Apoſtle enforced it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from his ſenſe of the neceſſity and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of it. For it is <hi>good</hi> in all thoſe reſpects which conduce to the good of Society, or the Intereſt of Mankind: <hi>good</hi> for the publick, and for every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man: <hi>good</hi> for them that rule, and for them that obey.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Good for the Publick,</hi> ſince it is not only eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to Society, but the foundation of all the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges we reap thereby; a Society cannot conſiſt without Union and Concord, but diſſolves into a rout, and unruly herd, when divided and diſuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and there can be neither Order nor Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where there is not mutual agreement; as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> obſerv'd of Thieves and Robbers, that they muſt agree together, and be true to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or elſe muſt needs diſſolve, and cannot hold together. For there is no other bond of publick Society, but <hi>Union,</hi> and when <hi>that</hi> is broke, all things tend to Ruin and Confuſion. But whilſt Unity is maintain'd, Society ſtands firm, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement always upholds a Government, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58190:11"/> thoſe publick bleſſings which we reap under the Safety and Protection of it. Where there is Unity, there is Peace; and Peace is the foundation of all thoſe advantages which conduce to our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick welfare. The great imperfection of this State is, that all things are tranſient and uncertain, and we are never ſecure of the happineſs we enjoy: and all the ſecurity we can have of thoſe favours which the bounty of Providence does indulge to us, is by the bleſſing of Quietneſs and Peace. 'Tis this preſerves <hi>Liberty and Property;</hi> 'tis this gives <hi>eaſe and plenty, and makes every man ſit down under his own Vine, and under his own figtree;</hi> to eat and drink the fruit of his labours, and taſte the ſweet of thoſe enjoyments which God has appointed for his Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and his Lot.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>'Tis good for every private man;</hi> which muſt needs be conſequent upon the former: ſince the benefit of publick bleſſings muſt needs redound to every particular perſon, and each man ſhares in the good of the Community. But beſides the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon advantages it affords of Peace and Safety, it largely contributes to each mans peculiar happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; chiefly in this reſpect, that it tends highly to beget that compoſedneſs of mind, and calm tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of ſoul, without which we cannot be happy in this life. Whatever ruffles a mans mind, robs him
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58190:12"/> alſo of his happineſs, and he that is diſquieted with Diſcord and Diſſention, <hi>cannot make his Soul enjoy good in his labour</hi> (as the wiſe man phraſes it.) But where there is kindneſs and correſpondence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe he converſes with, there is calmneſs and ſerenity; and as nothing diſturbs him from without, ſo he finds all eaſe and ſatisfaction from within; and thereby reaps that ineſtimable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of content and quiet of mind, which is the higheſt pitch of worldly felicity. So great is the excellency of this Virtue; it has an univerſal influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on all the happineſs we are capable of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here, and tends highly to the good of every man in what ſtation or capacity ſoever God has placed him.</p>
            <p>More particularly it tends directly to the ends of Government, which God under his Providence has made the inſtrument of the greateſt bleſſings which we are capable of in this life; and ſo it is further <hi>good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>For them that Rule;</hi> for where men are at U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity among themſelves, how eaſie is it to manage the reins of Government? How does it leſſen the burden that lies upon the ſhoulders of Governors? Certainly whatever men may pretend, they love not their Prince, nor are Friends to his felicity, who foment differences, and create Jealouſies and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58190:12"/> Diſcontents, which add to the cares of a <hi>Crown,</hi> and make the affairs of State difficult and uneaſie; they cannot be good Subjects who are always murmuring and querulous, uneaſie and unſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, turbulent and troubleſome, on all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions alarming their <hi>Rulers</hi> with fears and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicions, and ſtill keeping them awake to watch the deſigns of reſtleſs and unquiet Spirits. But where Subjects are quiet and peaceable, friends both to the State, and to one another, there a Kingdom proſpers, and Rulers reap the fruits of their Care and Vigilance in eaſe and plenty. Where People are unanimous, and do not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide themſelves into Parties and Factions, there need no penal Laws to reduce them to Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: and happy is that Government, where Reſtraint and Compulſion is needleſs: happy are thoſe Governours, whoſe People are of one mind; doubtleſs 'tis both their <hi>Security</hi> and their <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. <hi>'Tis good for them that Obey.</hi> For it leads directly to that end for which men are entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God with Power and Authority, which is <hi>that</hi> mentioned by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and made the ground of his Exhortation, <hi>That we put up Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Supplications for Kings, and for all that are in Authority, that under them we may lead quiet and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58190:13"/> peaceable lives in all godlineſs and honeſty,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 1, 2. But how can that end ever be attain'd? How can men lead <hi>quiet and peaceable lives,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Unity and Agreement? where Diſcord and Diſſention divide the Intereſts and Affections of Subjects from each other, they cannot ſo well enjoy the common Influence of their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours Care and Protection; and however ſuch peeviſh and angry men as foment ſtrife and diviſion, may think to wreak their ſpleen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the perſons of thoſe that are ſet over them, yet the miſchiefs of Diſcord and Diſagreement always chieflly redound upon the Subjects head, who thereby looſes thoſe bleſſings which Peace and Unity would have devolved upon him: Little do men think how much they contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to their own Ruine, who create Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and encreaſe Differences, to expoſe the Perſons of their Superiors, or weaken their Power and Authority: ſince the People muſt needs be unhappy, where they cannot lead <hi>quiet and peaceable lives;</hi> and to be ſure they have always the greateſt ſhare in the Evils of Anarchy and Confuſion. Let men talk what they will of their love to Religion and their Country, and delight to be called <hi>Patriots</hi> and <hi>Popular,</hi> yet they are no Friends to either, who are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58190:13"/> to Peace, and leaſt of all to the People, who ſuffer moſt in the loſs of it. But where Peace is preſerved, and Unity maintain'd, both Prince and People equally ſhare in the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of them, and rejoyce together in the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of Amity and Concord.</p>
            <p>You ſee in all theſe reſpects the neceſſity and uſefulneſs of Unity, how <hi>good</hi> it is, and it will appear no leſs pleaſant too. Which is the</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Its delight and comelineſs.</hi> For all Beauty ariſes from Proportion and Agreement; and there can be nothing lovely where there is not Harmony and Order: and among all the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of Unity, none more comely and grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to behold than that of Brethren, whoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry name imports <hi>Nearneſs</hi> and <hi>Conjunction,</hi> and their Relation implies <hi>Union</hi> and <hi>Familiarity;</hi> and where-ever we can ſee it acted, it affords the moſt grateful and raviſhing proſpect: and is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to behold, 1. <hi>To God.</hi> 2. <hi>To Angels.</hi> 3. <hi>To Good Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>To God,</hi> who made all things in Order and Harmony, and preſcrib'd them eternal Laws of Correſpondence and Agreement; and as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that he had made was very good, when he ſurveyed all the Works of his hands, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 31. So they continued to be ſo, till ſin
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58190:14"/> violated the Unity of the Creation, and firſt made a Breach and Diviſion among the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. But of all the Creatures, Man was the moſt lively Emblem of Unity, being framed for Society, and deſign'd for mutual love and friendſhip: and however the All-wiſe <hi>Creator,</hi> to ſhew the wonders of his Wiſdom and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, has made ſuch an infinite variety in the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of men, that whereas all conſiſt of the ſame kind and number of Parts, ſcarce two can be found wholly alike in Symmetry and Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet there is no ſuch diſproportion and diſſimilitude in the <hi>minds</hi> of men, but they are all caſt in the ſame Mold, adorn'd with the ſame Faculties, and endow'd with the ſame Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Reaſon, that thence they might all learn to agree in the ſame common Intereſts and Deſigns of Human Life: and whilſt man acts like himſelf, not only as a reaſonable, but a ſociable Creature, and delights to herd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with thoſe of his own kind, and makes uſe of the Principles of Nature and Reaſon, to the ends of Society, Correſpondence, and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and ſeeks not wholly himſelf, but the common good of Mankind, and ſtudies to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Peace of the World, God delights to behold ſuch agreeable Harmony, he is well
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58190:14"/> pleaſed with it: And indeed it reſembles that Celeſtial Society, whoſe Inhabitants dwell in the Regions of calmneſs and ſilence, that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Unity, where Peace and Order ſhall dwell together to eternal Ages.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>To the Angels,</hi> who being frequently em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by God in the affairs of Mankind, thoſe eſpecially that concern the methods of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in the Government of the World, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the welfare of Mankind, and delight in the Peace and Proſperity of the World: and as nothing more grateful to them, than to be Meſſengers of Peace, ſo do they evermore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce to ſee it flouriſh. How cheerfully did they publiſh the glad tidings of Peace and Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation? <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 14. even a whole Choire of thoſe Celeſtial Inhabitants joyned together in a Divine <hi>Anthem</hi> of Praiſe, to teſtifie their Joy and Exultation at the Proclamation <hi>of peace on earth, and good will towards men;</hi> and when-ever they deſcend from the Manſions of Peace, from the Kingdom of Order and Unity, they delight to behold the reſemblance of it upon Earth; which is highly pleaſing to thoſe kind Spirits, who wiſh well to the Sons of men, and well underſtand the advantages of Peace and Order, of love and kindneſs among men.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58190:15"/>
            <p>3. <hi>To Good Men,</hi> who as they moſtly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour after it, ſo more eſpecially delight to ſee it, and therein find real Content and ſolid Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; All the ſolid delight of this life conſiſts in good reflexions: whatever elſe may pretend to pleaſure, is but vain and imaginary; as the delights of ſenſe, which are but skin-deep; or the pleaſures of the World, which are but ſhews and appearances: that only is ſolid content which ariſes from the ſenſe and reflexions of true goodneſs; and that chiefly which condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the general good of Mankind, as Peace and Union moſt certainly do: ſo that they are pleaſant to the good man to behold, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyces in that raviſhing proſpect, and reaps the greateſt content and ſatisfaction in himſelf, to ſee the Beauty of Peace and Order, of Love and Kindneſs among men. So did St. <hi>Paul</hi> to ſee <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Uniformity</hi> flouriſh at <hi>Coloſs,</hi> Col. 2. 5, <hi>Joying, and beholding your Order, and the ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Faith in Chriſt;</hi> ſo do all good men, who not only pray for Unity in <hi>Sion,</hi> and Peace in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but delight to ſee it, and rejoyce together in the <hi>Pſalmiſts</hi> exaltation, <hi>behold, how good and pleaſant it is,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I know not what can more forcibly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the lovelineſs of <hi>Unity</hi> to you, than theſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58190:15"/> Conſiderations of its <hi>neceſſity</hi> and <hi>Uſefulneſs,</hi> of <hi>its delight and comelineſs, 'tis both good and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant.</hi> If any thing can further endear it, it would be the deſcription of the miſchiefs of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion and Diſſention, of Confuſion and Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: as contraries beſt illuſtrate each other; and ſprightly Colours are beſt ſet off when drawn on a dark ground. But I have not time to draw ſo large a Scene.</p>
            <p>Suffice it to ſay, that the want of Unity and Agreement among Brethren, is the ground of all thoſe Evils which obſtruct the proſperity of the Church, or diſturb the Peace of the World; and ſo is neither <hi>good,</hi> nor <hi>pleaſant,</hi> but directly oppoſite to both in all the forenamed Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. St <hi>James</hi> ſaid rightly, 3. 16. <hi>Where envying and ſtrife is, there is confuſion, and every evil work:</hi> and I am ſure <hi>that</hi> is neither <hi>good</hi> nor <hi>pleaſant</hi> to behold.</p>
            <p>Not good for the <hi>Publick,</hi> whoſe Peace it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, and endangers its Safety. Not good for <hi>private men,</hi> whoſe Intereſt is ſo much twiſted in the publick welfare, that they cannot be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py without it. Not good for them that <hi>rule,</hi> ſince how skilful Pilots ſoever ſit at the Helm of State, they may be overwhelm'd with the Waves of Sedition, and the violent Hurricanes of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58190:16"/> Mutiny and Faction. Not good for them that <hi>obey,</hi> ſince it fruſtrates the ends of Society, Peace and Security, and leaves every man expoſed to the Violence and Inſolency of licentious men. Nor is it any whit more <hi>pleaſant</hi> to behold. Not to <hi>God,</hi> who as he is the God of Peace and Order, ſo he delights to ſee them maintain'd and flouriſh: but that which creates Confuſion and Diſorder, not only diſturbs that Harmony and Concord which he eſtabliſhed among the Creatures, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects diſhonour upon his Providence, and makes men queſtion the Equity of his proceedings.</p>
            <p>Not to <hi>Angels;</hi> unleſs it be thoſe malignant Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits who <hi>kept not their firſt ſtation,</hi> and ever ſince they were baniſht Heaven, being caſt too low to make any further diſturbance there, have made it their buſineſs to oppoſe the methods of Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence on Earth; and no doubt rejoyce to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyl the World with diſorder and miſchief: but not ſo the <hi>good Angels,</hi> who are employed in meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages for the good of Mankind, and rejoyce in the Peace and Order of the World. Not to <hi>good men;</hi> who grieve at the diſorders and miſcarriages of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and like <hi>David,</hi> fret their righteous ſouls even with <hi>dwelling among them that are enemies unto peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are ſeveral reſpects more in which I might expoſe the Evils that are conſequent upon
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58190:16"/> the want of Peace and Unity; the miſeries that attend Diviſion and Diſſention: and that diſmal Scene would add grace and luſtre to this proſpect of <hi>Unity</hi> which is ſo pleaſant to behold. But it needs no foil to ſet its Beauty: and therefore I ſhall content my ſelf with the Deſcription already given of it in the Characters of <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Pleaſant,</hi> which are forcible attractives of our Love and Choice.</p>
            <p>But that I may further recommend it to you, I ſhall ſtrengthen my Argument from the Seaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of it, that it ought now more eſpecially to be embraced: chiefly from theſe two <hi>Conſiderations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>That our Enemies are United.</hi> There have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been ſuch as hate <hi>Sion:</hi> the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent has hatch'd a Generation of Vipers, that has always malign'd goodneſs, and perſecuted Gods Church and People: and they are Brethren in Iniquity, Confederated together, and joyntly carry on their Hatred and Enmity. I need not tell you who are the Enemies of our <hi>Sion;</hi> nor point at them whom every man may behold, and ſee them at once combin'd againſt us, and induſtrious to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine us. Is not the Church endangered by Schiſm, and the State by Factions and Combinations? Are not the Enemies of our Peace as buſie as ever to embroil us? And the ſame Engins employed to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58190:17"/> undermine our Foundations? By the <hi>Papiſts</hi> we are ſtill condemn'd for <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks:</hi> and how are they combin'd by Oaths and Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by Vows and Obligations, to extirpate <hi>Hereſie?</hi> and if we look that way, may we not ſee the <hi>Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> and the <hi>Iſhmaelites,</hi> the <hi>Moabites</hi> and <hi>Hagarens, Gebal,</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Amalek,</hi> the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> and <hi>them of Tyre,</hi> all gnaſhing their teeth at us, and gaping to devour us?</p>
            <p>Neither does all our danger blow from that Quarter. For have we not Traytors within our own Walls that are no leſs ſedulous to betray us, and as unanimous in their Hatred and Oppoſition to us? Have not <hi>Diſſenters</hi> of all ſorts united a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, who were never at one either among themſelves, or with any Church of Chriſt? Have not Arts been uſed to get <hi>them</hi> own'd for <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> who were never yet <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> rather than want a Party to carry on the Deſigns of Schiſm and Faction? Are not they who formerly entred into a <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> againſt our eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church, Projecting a new, but more wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and dangerous <hi>Aſſociation?</hi> And is it not then high time for them to unite, who wiſh well to the Government both of Church and State? Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we may learn Wiſdom from our Enemies; that ſince they are ſo diligent to Confederate together
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58190:17"/> for our ruin, we may fruſtrate their Attempts by the ſame Methods of Unity and Agreement. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when we conſider,</p>
            <p>2. <hi>That there is no other apparent means of ſafety.</hi> Our Saviour ſaid, <hi>A Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand.</hi> When our Diviſions are ſo many, what can heal our Breaches but Unity? 'Tis well known how fatal the Diviſions of Chriſtians have been to the Peace of Chriſtendom. The <hi>Turk</hi> had never enlarged his Territories ſo far, had not the Diſſenſions of thoſe that ſhould have oppoſed him made way for him. Nor can any thing ſo ſoon put a ſtop to his growing Greatneſs, as the Peace and Union of Chriſtian Princes, and nothing has more endangered the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> ſince the happy Reformation of it, than the Diviſions of Proteſtants among themſelves. The <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Conclave</hi> know it too well; and fear nothing ſo much as the Union of Proteſtants; nor envy any reformed Church ſo much as ours, and therefore uſe all their Arts and Emiſſaries to embroyl us, and divide us into Factions and Parties; thereby at once weakning our Intereſt, and ſtrengthning their own. 'Tis ſtrange indeed that men of ſenſe and reaſon ſhould not diſcern the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> in the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> Diſguiſe, when he has ſo long frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſo frequently Preach'd in moſt ſeparate
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58190:18"/> Meetings. 'Tis more ſtrange that they that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſo much Zeal againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> ſhould oppoſe that <hi>Church.</hi> which is the only regular Bulwark and Defence againſt it. 'Tis moſt of all ſtrange that the moſt active <hi>true Proteſtants</hi> (as they call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) ſhould be the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> chiefeſt Engine, and beſt Friends to <hi>Rome.</hi> Yet plain it is, that men may go to <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Geneva;</hi> and many that ſeem to Travel to the latter, are poſting directly to the former. 'Tis to be feared 'tis no unfrequented path, and is found the ſecureſt way to paſs unſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected. He knows little that ſees not how like to each other they are both in Principles and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; that the <hi>Diſſenter</hi> ſharpens his Weapons at the forge of the <hi>Romiſh Philiſtines;</hi> and that the <hi>Covenanter</hi> and <hi>Aſſociator</hi> act but what the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> Teaches: And however ſome men meaſure their Zeal to the Reformed Religion by their Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ground all their Cavils againſt our eſtabliſh'd Church on pretended fears and ſuſpicions, yet I think no wiſe man needs to doubt, but to widen our breaches is the readieſt way to let in <hi>Popery.</hi> God at laſt open their eyes, that they may ſee their danger, and diſcover their miſtake! and in his mercy turn their hearts (as <hi>David</hi> once bowed the hearts of the men of <hi>Judah) as one man,</hi> 2 Sam. 19. 14. That they may be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58190:18"/> in their Allegiance to the <hi>King,</hi> and hearty in the Religion of our <hi>Church;</hi> and then we need not fear the craft of the <hi>Conclave,</hi> nor the Deſigns of the <hi>Conſiſtory.</hi> Were all men but truly ſenſible of the advantages of Unity, they would endeavour after it. Were we ſo united, we ſhould be happy.</p>
            <p>And that we may every one in our ſeveral Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities contribute our hearty endeavours hereto, I ſhall cloſe up the Exhortation with a twofold Direction of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> both ſuitable to our Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, both highly conducing to the ends of <hi>Union and Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. The firſt is his advice to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1 Ep. 4. 11, <hi>Study to be quiet, and to do your own buſineſs.</hi> Would men do their own buſineſs, they would find work enough at home: would they ſtudy to be quiet, they would not buſie themſelves in other mens matters. And never more need of this advice than in this Pragmatical Age, wherein men ſtudy to be unquiet, and make it their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment to meddle in other mens Concerns. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every man ſets up for a Politician, or Reformer of Religion; and ſhall pretend to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate to his Superiors, how to manage affairs of State, and compoſe differences in the Church. Every Club of idle and talkative Perſons, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as Cenſorious and Dogmatical, as if they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58190:19"/> were as wiſe as a <hi>Council-Table,</hi> and as Judicious in Religion as a <hi>Convocation.</hi> God knows 'tis the fault of the Age; and God grant it prove not fatal to our Peace and Happineſs. For alaſs! we have already almoſt talk'd the State into Confuſion, and Religion into Atheiſm, or Indifferency, which is little better. The beſt on't is, ſuch Buſie-bodies are uſually catch'd in their own ſnares; and it has oft been found dangerous to intrude into another mans Office or Employment. <hi>Uzzah</hi> would needs put forth his hand to hold the Ark, and was ſtruck dead, becauſe he medled with that which was none of his buſineſs, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 6, 7. <hi>Uzziah</hi> inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Prieſts Office, and would burn Incenſe, but while the Cenſer was in his hand, his ſin was writ on his forehead, he was ſtruck with a Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and cut off from the Houſe of the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron. 26. 16. Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> were <hi>Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the Earth ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them up. <hi>Sheba</hi> blew a Trumpet of Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſoon after his head was thrown over the wall. <hi>Abſolom</hi> was too buſie with the Kings af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and would needs ſit in the <hi>Tribunal,</hi> but was hanged in the Oak as a fitter place for him; and we may eaſily call to mind ſome very lately a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves, that have talk'd themſelves into an Halter, and found how fatal it is to be too tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58190:19"/> ſawcy and medling. Better far for us to do our own buſineſs with quietneſs, and leave o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men to do theirs: and in ſo doing we ſhall find no difficulty from our ſelves, nor diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from others. Let us reſolve to be faithful to our own buſineſs, and leave others to the duties of their Station, and content our ſelves with the choice Providence has made for us, and not pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhly think to be our own Carvers. <hi>Every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>Rom. 12. 4, has not the ſame Office.</hi> Having therefore different Callings, Gifts, and Places, let every man wait upon, and move in his own, and therein ſtudy to be quiet, and do his own buſineſs. Let the <hi>Lawyer</hi> Plead; and the <hi>Merchant</hi> Trade: let <hi>Rulers</hi> make Laws, and their <hi>Subjects</hi> keep them: let the <hi>King</hi> Govern, and the <hi>People</hi> Obey him: let the <hi>Miniſter</hi> Preach and Pray; and let the <hi>People</hi> ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi> And if we thus do our own buſineſs, <hi>we ſhall</hi> (like Brethren) <hi>dwell together in Unity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if there be amongſt you <hi>Tatlers</hi> and <hi>Buſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodies,</hi> Medlers in State, or Bigots in Religion, that value not the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> excellent advice, I leave with you another Direction of <hi>his</hi> proper for them, which is,</p>
            <p>2. The Caution he gives to the <hi>Romans, 16. 17. Mark them which cauſe Diviſions and Offences, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58190:20"/> avoid them;</hi> beware of their Inſinuations, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain their Converſe and Familiarity, and ſet a <hi>mark</hi> upon them. I mean not a <hi>mark</hi> of private Grudg and Revenge, but of turbulent reſtleſs Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, whoſe ill ſuggeſtions are not to be credited, whoſe Diſſenſions are to be avoided; a <hi>mark</hi> of Shame and Diſgrace, that if their own impudence will not let them bluſh, others may be aſhamed of their folly; a <hi>mark</hi> of Infamy and Reproach, that we may ſhun their Company; ſince an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Peace is no mans friend, and every Author of Miſchief and Diſturbance, is to be lookt upon as a common Peſt, and publick Nuiſance. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a <hi>mark</hi> of Diſtinction, which the Laws ſet on them; and were they duly put in Execution, would be the ſureſt Antidote againſt the Poyſon of their envenom'd Tongues, the malice of their ſeditious whiſpers; and let none think it Cruelty or Severity to have ſuch men made exemplary, as ſlander the Government, and calumniate their Governours, ſince they are men that obey more for Wrath, than for Conſcience ſake: whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can reſtrain but fear of the Penalty; and without ſuch a reſtraint, no Government can be ſafe or quiet: and let the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> know that in this reſpect he <hi>bears not the ſword in vain;</hi> but that it ought chiefly to be drawn againſt ſuch offenders
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58190:20"/> as foment Diſſentions, and diſturb publick Peace and Tranquillity.</p>
            <p>I hope there is no great need in this Place to preſs the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to his Duty in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; nor any great Occaſion for it. I am confident there would be far leſs need of it, were but theſe two directions of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, were ſuch as <hi>cauſe Diviſions, avoided,</hi> and would <hi>we all ſtudy to be quiet, and do our own bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs.</hi> I know nothing more effectual to that <hi>Unity</hi> which I have all along recommended; nor any means more certain to make us an happy People; happy are you if you know and value your own happineſs: which doubtleſs you will, if all that has been ſaid to endear Unity and Agreement, has had its due effect upon all that hear me. It has been a ſcandal thrown on ſeveral <hi>Corporations,</hi> that they have been Nurſeries of Schiſm and Faction. May it never be the complaint of yours: but rather may your Amity and Friendſhip be as peculiar and remarkable as your <hi>Guild;</hi> and your Unity be Publiſhed, where-ever that is Proclaimed, and may it not only like your <hi>Franchiſes</hi> be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed once in <hi>twenty years,</hi> but continued all that Time, and maintain'd inviolable, that <hi>ſucceſſive Generations</hi> may ſtill behold amongſt you the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58190:21"/> ſame grateful proſpect of Brotherly Love and Kindneſs, and <hi>twenty years</hi> hence rejoyce to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in your Example <hi>how good and pleaſant it is for Brethren to dwell together in Unity.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Now to the God of Unity, Peace, and Order, to the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and One God, be all Honour, Glory, and Praiſe, now and for evermore. Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:58190:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
